As I mentioned, you communicate top-down, but you actually build your argument bottom-up.
So first you start with the myriad of facts and details that you have around what you want to communicate,
and you spend some time laying them out and trying to group them logically.
It’s not always obvious how to do it. I’ve been working with a commercial bank going through a large-scale transformation, trying to deliver more value to their customers.
The head of the commercial bank has been working on how she’s going to communicate this to her organization.
There are about 25 independent initiatives going on that are going to drive this result.
And when you take all 25 and lay them out, it’s not exactly obvious how they all roll up to drive the outcome that they’re trying to achieve.
And that’s what she’s working on: how to communicate that in a way that’s very clear and easy to understand.
When you look at all the initiatives, some of them are around transforming the way customers interact with the bank.
Some of them are around how people work internally in the shared services function, in order to deliver smoother processes.
And it’s not clear where those initiatives belong. Some of them feel more internal; some of them actually feel more customer-facing.
And so they’re taking some time moving things around between those two.
There’s a third category of things they’re doing, which are really around unlocking human potential and talent in the organization.
But as they look at those initiatives, it’s not clear if some of those are more of the internal ways-of-working initiatives, or actually human capital initiatives.
And so the point is that it takes time, and it’s not always obvious.
Your arguments need to be comprehensive — you shouldn’t leave anything out — but they also need to be mutually exclusive. For short, we say: no gaps or overlaps.
So rather than seeing 25 individual, discrete activities happening, her organization now sees three thematic
programs, with many different things happening underneath them. But they understand how those different things are coming together to drive to the greater outcome.
One thing I saw once, which I thought was incredibly powerful, was when an executive was preparing for a presentation to that company’s most important client,
and there were all sorts of messages they wanted to communicate,
and we went through an exercise where we wrote all those messages down on post-it notes.
And what we came to see is that those messages were all at different levels.
Some were really important, almost summary kind of messages, or they were what we might call the governing thought.
Other messages were important tactical points to make.
And when you started looking at all the messages together, you started to see that they actually grouped into three themes.
And you saw that those three themes were very powerful, and that when you put them together, they hung together into one overall message about the power that this executive and their biggest client could collectively get from their relationship.
And so what began as a communication which was going to be, I would say, almost a laundry list of different messages, became a very structured argument,
with a governing or key thought, the three most important things which elevate into that governing thought, and then a series of specific points which supported that,
all nested and communicated in a very well-crafted way. And it was extremely powerful to sit and watch that unfold, and watch that communication have the desired impact.